from the Armed Islamic Group with a paring knife?
من الجماعة الإسلامية المسلحة بواسطة سكين التقشير؟
That was the question I faced
ذلك هو السؤال الذي واجهني
one Tuesday morning in June of 1993,
صباح يوم ثلاثاء في يونيو 1993،
when I was a law student.
عندما كنت طالبة حقوق.
I woke up early that morning
استيقظت باكراً ذلك الصباح
in Dad's apartment
في شقة والدي
on the outskirts of Algiers, Algeria,
في ضواحي الجزائر العاصمة، في الجزائر،
to an unrelenting pounding on the front door.
على طرقٍ بلا هوادة على الباب الأمامي.
It was a season as described by a local paper
في موسم وصفته الصحف المحلية
when every Tuesday a scholar fell
بسقوط باحث كل يوم ثلاثاء
to the bullets of fundamentalist assassins.
برصاص القتلة الأصوليين.
My father's university teaching of Darwin
لقد انجرّ عن تدريس والدي في الجامعة لنظرية داروين
had already provoked a classroom visit
زيارة في الصف الدراسي
from the head of the so-called Islamic Salvation Front,
من قبل رئيس ما يسمى بجبهة التحريرالإسلامي،
who denounced Dad as an advocate of biologism
الذي اتهم والدي بأنه داعية للحتمية الأحيائية
before Dad had ejected the man,
قبل أن يطرده والدي،
and now whoever was outside
والآن أياً كان من بالخارج
would neither identify himself nor go away.
فهو لم يعرّف بنفسه ولم يكن ليرحل.
So my father tried to get the police on the phone,
قام والدي بالاتصال بالشرطة،
but perhaps terrified by the rising tide
لكنهم ربما كانوا خائفين من ارتفاع درجة خطورة
of armed extremism that had already claimed
مع المتطرفين المسلحين والذين سبق و أن حصدوا
the lives of so many Algerian officers,
أرواح العديد من الضباط الجزائريين،
they didn't even answer.
لدرجة أنهم لم يجيبوا على الهاتف.
And that was when I went to the kitchen,
عندها اتجهت إلى المطبخ
got out a paring knife,
وتناولت سكين تقشير،
and took up a position inside the entryway.
واتخذت موضع استعداد داخل مدخل البيت.
It was a ridiculous thing to do, really,
كان من الحماقة فعل ذلك حينها حقاً،
but I couldn't think of anything else,
لكن لم يخطر ببالي أمر غير ذلك،
and so there I stood.
وهناك وقفت.
When I look back now, I think that that was the moment
عندما أتذكر ذلك الآن، أعتقد أن تلك اللحظة
that set me on the path was to writing a book
هي التي وضعتني على طريق تأليف كتاب
called "Your Fatwa Does Not Apply Here:
يسمى " فتواك لا تنطبق هنا :
Untold Stories from the Fight Against Muslim Fundamentalism."
قصص لم ترو من الحرب ضد الأصولية الإسلامية."
The title comes from a Pakistani play.
استُقيَ العنوان من مسرحية باكستانية.
I think it was actually that moment
أعتقد حقيقةً أن تلك اللحظة
that sent me on the journey
هي التي أرسلتني في رحلة
to interview 300 people of Muslim heritage
لمقابلة 300 شخص من المسلمين
from nearly 30 countries,
في حوالي 30 دولة،
from Afghanistan to Mali,
من أفغانستان إلى مالي،
to find out how they fought fundamentalism
لاستكشاف كيف حاربوا الأصولية
peacefully like my father did,
سلمياً كما فعل والدي،
and how they coped with the attendant risks.
وكيف تعاملوا مع المخاطر المصاحبة.
Luckily, back in June of 1993,
لحسن الحظ، في يونيو 1993،
our unidentified visitor went away,
رحل زائرنا المجهول،
but other families were so much less lucky,
لكن عائلات أخرى كانت أقل حظاً بكثير،
and that was the thought that motivated my research.
وتلك كانت الفكرة التي حفّزت بحثي.
In any case, someone would return
على أي حال، عاد أحدهم
a few months later and leave a note
بعد عدة أشهر، وترك رسالة
on Dad's kitchen table,
على طاولة مطبخ والدي،
which simply said, "Consider yourself dead."
تقول ببساطة ،" اعتبر نفسك ميتاً."
Subsequently, Algeria's fundamentalist armed groups
بعد ذلك، قامت الجماعات الأصولية المسلحة في الجزائر
would murder as many as 200,000 civilians
بقتل أكثر من 200,000 مدني
in what came to be known
فيما عُرف
as the dark decade of the 1990s,
بالعشرية السوداء في التسعينيات،
including every single one
بما فيهم كل من هؤلاء
of the women that you see here.
النساء اللاتي ترونهن هنا.
In its harsh counterterrorist response,
وفي رد قاس ٍ ومضاد ،
the state resorted to torture
لجأت الدولة للتعذيب
and to forced disappearances,
و الإختفاء القسري،
and as terrible as all of these events became,
و بالرغم من السوء الذي وصلت له كل هذه الأحداث،
the international community largely ignored them.
فقد تجاهلها المجتمع الدولي بشكل كبير.
Finally, my father, an Algerian peasant's son turned professor,
أخيراً، والدي،الجزائري ابن الفلاحين، أصبح أستاذا،
was forced to stop teaching at the university
أُجبر على التوقف عن التدريس في الجامعة
and to flee his apartment,
وإخلاء شقته،
but what I will never forget
لكن ما لن أنساه أبداً
about Mahfoud Bennoune, my dad,
عن والدي،محفوظ بنّون،
was that like so many other Algerian intellectuals,
أنه كان مثل العديد من المثقفين الجزائريين الآخرين،
he refused to leave the country
قد رفض مغادرة البلاد
and he continued to publish pointed criticisms,
واستمر في نشر انتقادات حادة،
both of the fundamentalists
لكل من الأصوليين
and sometimes of the government they battled.
وبعض الأحيان للدولة التي كانوا يحاربونها.
For example, in a November 1994 series
على سبيل المثال،نُشِرت سلسلة في نونبر 1994
in the newspaper El Watan
في صحيفة الوطن
entitled "How Fundamentalism
بعنوان " كيف أنتجت الأصولية
Produced a Terrorism without Precedent,"
إرهابا لا سابقة له،"
he denounced what he called
ندّد بما أسماه
the terrorists' radical break with the true Islam
اختلاف الإرهابيين الجذري عن الإسلام الحقيقي
as it was lived by our ancestors.
كما عايشه أسلافنا.
These were words that could get you killed.
كانت هذه كلمات قد تتسبب في قتلك.
My father's country taught me
علمتني بلاد والدي
in that dark decade of the 1990s that
في تلك العشرية السوداء بالتسعينيات
the popular struggle against Muslim fundamentalism
أن الصراع الشهير ضد الأصوليين الإسلاميين
is one of the most important
هو واحد من أهم صراعات
and overlooked human rights struggles
حقوق الإنسان وأكثرها تجاهلاً
in the world.
في العالم.
This remains true today, nearly 20 years later.
مازال ذلك صحيحاً حتى اليوم، بعد حوالي 20 سنة.
You see, in every country
ترون، في كل دولة
where you hear about armed jihadis
تسمعون فيها عن المسلحين الجهاديين
targeting civilians,
الذين يستهدفون المدنيين،
there are also unarmed people
هنالك أيضاً أناس غير مسلحين
defying those militants that you don't hear about,
يواجهون تلك المليشيات لكن لا تسمعون عنهم،
and those people need our support to succeed.
ووهؤلاء الناس يحتاجون دعمنا لينجحوا.
In the West, it's often assumed
في الغرب،غالباً ما يفترض
that Muslims generally condone terrorism.
أن المسلمين بشكل عام يتغاضون عن الإرهاب.
Some on the right think this because they view
بعض اليمينيين يعتقد ذلك لأنهم يرون
Muslim culture as inherently violent,
أن الثقافة الإسلامية عنيفة بطبعها،
and some on the left imagine this
وبعض اليساريين يتخيلون ذلك
because they view Muslim violence,
لأنهم يرون العنف الإسلامي،
fundamentalist violence,
العنف المتطرف،
solely as a product of legitimate grievances.
على أنه مجرد نتيجة للمظالم المشروعة.
But both views are dead wrong.
لكن كلتا الرؤيتين خاطئة بشدة.
In fact, many people of Muslim heritage
في الواقع،أغلب الناس من المسلمين
around the world are staunch opponents
حول العالم يعارضون بشدة
both of fundamentalism and of terrorism,
كلا من الأصولية والإرهاب،
and often for very good reason.
وغالباً لسبب وجيه جدا.
You see, they're much more likely to be victims
أترون، من المرجح جدا أن يكونوا ضحايا
of this violence than its perpetrators.
لهذا العنف أكثر من مرتكبيه.
Let me just give you one example.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالا واحدا.
According to a 2009 survey
تبعاً لإحصائية في 2009
of Arabic language media resources,
مصدرها الإعلام الناطق باللغة العربية،
between 2004 and 2008,
بين 2004 و 2008
no more than 15 percent of al Qaeda's victims
أقل من 15% فقط من ضحايا القاعدة
were Westerners.
كانوا من الغربيين.
That's a terrible toll, but the vast majority
تلك حصيلة مروعة،لكن الغالبية العظمى
were people of Muslim heritage,
كانوا من المسلمين،
killed by Muslim fundamentalists.
قتلوا من طرف المتطرفين الإسلاميين.
Now I've been talking for the last five minutes
أثناء الخمس الدقائق الماضية وأنا أتحدث
about fundamentalism, and you have a right to know
عن الأصولية، والآن لديكم الحق لتعرفوا
exactly what I mean.
ما أعنيه بالضبط.
I cite the definition given by the Algerian sociologist
أستشهد بتعريف أعطته عالمة الإجتماع الجزائرية
Marieme Helie Lucas,
مريم هيلي لوكاس،
and she says that fundamentalisms,
تقول أن الأصوليات هي،
note the "s," so within all of the world's
لاحظوا الجمع، في جميع ثقافات
great religious traditions,
العالم الدينية العظيمة،
"fundamentalisms are political movements of the extreme right
" الأصوليات هي حركات سياسية لليمين المتطرف
which in a context of globalization
والتي في سياق العولمة
manipulate religion in order to achieve
تتلاعب بالدين في سبيل تحقيق
their political aims."
أهدافها السياسية."
Sadia Abbas has called this the radical politicization
سعدية عباس أسمته التسييس المتطرف
of theology.
للاهوت.
Now I want to avoid projecting the notion
هنا أريد أن أتجنب إسقاط النظرية
that there's sort of a monolith out there
القائلة بأن هناك نوع من الكتلة الواحدة
called Muslim fundamentalism that is the same everywhere,
تسمى الأصولية الإسلامية والمتشابهة في كل مكان،
because these movements also have their diversities.
لأن هذه الحركات لها أيضاً تشعباتها.
Some use and advocate violence.
يستخدم البعض العنف ويدعو له.
Some do not, though they're often interrelated.
والبعض الآخر ليس كذلك، لكنهم غالباً مترابطون.
They take different forms.
هم يأخذون أشكالاً مختلفة.
Some may be non-governmental organizations,
قد يكون البعض منظمات غير حكومية،
even here in Britain like Cageprisoners.
حتى هنا في بريطانيا مثل منظمة "سجناء الأقفاص".
Some may become political parties,
و قد يصبح البعض أحزابا سياسية،
like the Muslim Brotherhood,
مثل الأخوان المسلمين،
and some may be openly armed groups
والبعض الآخر قد يكون مجموعات مسلحة علنية
like the Taliban.
مثل حركة طالبان.
But in any case, these are all radical projects.
لكن بشكل عام،كل هذه تعتبر مشاريع متطرفة.
They're not conservative or traditional approaches.
ليست مناهج تقليدية أو محافظة.
They're most often about changing people's relationship with Islam
تكون فكرتها غالبا عن تغييرعلاقة الناس بالإسلام
rather than preserving it.
بدلاً من الحفاظ عليها.
What I am talking about is the Muslim extreme right,
ما أتكلم عنه هو التطرف الإسلامي اليميني،
and the fact that its adherents are
وكون أن أتباعه هم مسلمون
or purport to be Muslim
أو يدّعون بأنهم كذلك
makes them no less offensive
لا يجعلهم أقل عدوانية
than the extreme right anywhere else.
من المتطرفين اليمينيين في أي مكان آخر.
So in my view, if we consider ourselves
في نظري،لو اعتبرنا أنفسنا
liberal or left-wing,
متحررين أو يساريين
human rights-loving or feminist,
أو محبين لحقوق الإنسان أو مساواة حقوق المرأة،
we must oppose these movements
يجب أن نقاوم هذه الحركات
and support their grassroots opponents.
وندعم معارضيها السياسيين من الشعب.
Now let me be clear
ودعوني أكون واضحة هنا
that I support an effective struggle
أنا أدعم صراعا فعّالا
against fundamentalism,
ضد التطرف،
but also a struggle that must itself
لكن على هذا الصراع نفسه أيضا
respect international law,
أن يحترم القانون الدولي،
so nothing I am saying should be taken
لذلك لا يجب أن يؤخذ شيء مما أقوله
as a justification for refusals
كمبرر لرفض
to democratize,
الديموقراطية،
and here I send out a shout-out of support
ومن هنا أرسل دعمي وبصوت عال
to the pro-democracy movement in Algeria today, Barakat.
للحركة المؤيدة للديموقراطية في الجزائر اليوم،بركات.
Nor should anything I say be taken
ولا يجب أن يؤخذ شيء مما أقوله
as a justification of violations of human rights,
كمبرر للعنف ضد حقوق الإنسان،
like the mass death sentences
مثل الأحكام الكثيرة بالإعدام
handed out in Egypt earlier this week.
التي صدرت في مصر هذا الأسبوع.
But what I am saying
ما أقوله هو
is that we must challenge these Muslim fundamentalist movements
أننا يجب أن نتحدى هذه الحركات الأصولية الإسلامية
because they threaten human rights
لأنها تهدد حقوق الإنسان
across Muslim-majority contexts,
من خلال استغلال الغالبية المسلمة،
and they do this in a range of ways,
ويفعلون ذلك بعدة طرق مختلفة،
most obviously with the direct attacks on civilians
أوضحها هو الهجوم المباشر على المواطنين
by the armed groups that carry those out.
من طرف المجموعات المسلحة التي تتبنى هذه العلميات.
But that violence is just the tip of the iceberg.
لكن ذلك العنف هو فقط ما يرى من قمة جبل الجليد.
These movements as a whole purvey discrimination
تغذي هذه الحركات بشكل عام التمييز
against religious minorities and sexual minorities.
ضد الأقليات الدينية والأقليات الجنسية.
They seek to curtail the freedom of religion
يسعون إلى سلب حرية الدين
of everyone who either practices in a different way
لكل شخص يطبقه بطريقة مختلفة
or chooses not to practice.
أو اختار أن لا يطبقه.
And most definingly, they lead an all-out war
والأكثر وضوحاً،أنهم يقودون حرب شاملة
on the rights of women.
ضد حقوق المرأة.
Now, faced with these movements
بعد مواجهة هذه الحركات
in recent years, Western discourse
في السنوات الأخيرة ، قدّم الخطاب الغربي
has most often offered
غالباً
two flawed responses.
رأيين خاطئين.
The first that one sometimes finds on the right
الأول ما نجده أحياناً يمينياً
suggests that most Muslims are fundamentalist
يقترح أن أغلب المسلمين متطرفون
or something about Islam is inherently fundamentalist,
أو يرى أشياء في الإسلام متطرفة بطبيعتها ،
and this is just offensive and wrong,
وهذا ببساطة عدواني وخاطئ،
but unfortunately on the left one sometimes encounters
لكن للأسف نواجه في اليسار أحياناً
a discourse that is too politically correct
خطابا يقول أنه يصح سياسياً
to acknowledge the problem of Muslim fundamentalism at all
الاعتراف بمشكلة التطرف الإسلامي بشكل عام
or, even worse, apologizes for it,
أو حتى أسوأ من ذلك،الإعتذار عنها،
and this is unacceptable as well.
وذلك أيضاً غير مقبول.
So what I'm seeking is a new way
ما أبحث عنه هو طريقة جديدة
of talking about this all together,
للحديث عن هذا كله،
which is grounded in the lived experiences
و الذي يتأصل في الخبرات المعاشة
and the hope of the people on the front lines.
وآمال الناس في الجبهات الأمامية.
I'm painfully aware that there has been
أنا أعي بألم أن هناك
an increase in discrimination against Muslims in recent years
تمييزا متزايدا ضد المسلمين في السنوات الأخيرة
in countries like the U.K. and the U.S.,
في دول مثل بريطانيا وأمريكا،
and that too is a matter of grave concern,
وذلك أيضاً أمر يدعو للقلق البالغ،
but I firmly believe
لكن أؤمن بشدة
that telling these counter-stereotypical stories
أن الإخبار بهذه القصص المكافحة للنمطية
of people of Muslim heritage
عن أناس من التراث الإسلامية
who have confronted the fundamentalists
والذين واجهوا الأصوليين
and been their primary victims
وكانوا هم ضحاياهم الأوائل
is also a great way of countering that discrimination.
هي أيضاً طريقة عظيمة في مواجهة التمييز.
So now let me introduce you
والآن دعوني أقدم لكم
to four people whose stories
أربعة أشخاص رواية قصصهم
I had the great honor of telling.
تعتبر شرفا عظيما لي.
Faizan Peerzada and the Rafi Peer Theatre
فايزان بيرزاده ومسرح رافي بير
workshop named for his father
ورشة عمل سُميّت باسم والده
have for years promoted the performing arts
روجت لعدة سنوات للفنون الاستعراضية
in Pakistan.
في باكستان .
With the rise of jihadist violence,
مع ارتفاع عنف الجهاديين،
they began to receive threats
بدأوا في تلقي تهديدات
to call off their events, which they refused to heed.
تدعوهم لإيقاف فعالياتهم، والتي رفضوا الإذعان لها.
And so a bomber struck their 2008
في 2008 ضربت قنبلة
eighth world performing arts festival in Lahore,
مهرجانهم الفني العالمي الثامن في لاهور،
producing rain of glass
خلفت أمطارا من الزجاج
that fell into the venue
تساقطت على المسرح
injuring nine people,
وأصابت 9 أشخاص،
and later that same night,
ولاحقاً في نفس تلك الليلة،
the Peerzadas made a very difficult decision:
اتخذت عائلة بيرزاده قراراً صعباً جداً:
they announced that their festival
فقدأعلنوا أن مهرجانهم
would continue as planned the next day.
سيستمر في اليوم التالي كما هو مخطط له.
As Faizan said at the time,
كما قال فايزان حينها،
if we bow down to the Islamists,
لو خضعنا للإسلاميين،
we'll just be sitting in a dark corner.
سنبقى منغلقين في زاوية مظلمة.
But they didn't know what would happen.
لم تكن لديهم فكرة عن ما سيحدث.
Would anyone come?
هل سيحضر أي أحد؟
In fact, thousands of people came out the next day
في الواقع ،قدم آلاف الناس في اليوم التالي
to support the performing arts in Lahore,
لدعم الفنون الاستعراضية في لاهور،
and this simultaneously thrilled
وذلك في نفس الوقت أسعد
and terrified Faizan,
وأخاف فايزان،
and he ran up to a woman
وهرع إلى امرأة
who had come in with her two small children,
قدمت مع ابنيها الصغيرين،
and he said, "You do know there was a bomb here yesterday,
وقال لها ،" أنتِ تعلمين أنه كانت هنا قنبلة بالأمس،
and you do know there's a threat here today."
وتعلمين أننا مازلنا مهددين اليوم."
And she said, "I know that,
فردّت،"أعلم ذلك،
but I came to your festival
لكني قدمت إلى مهرجانكم
with my mother when I was their age,
مع أمي عندما كنت في عمرهم،
and I still have those images in my mind.
ومازلت احتفظ بتلك الصور في مخيلتي.
We have to be here."
يجب أن نكون هنا."
With stalwart audiences like this,
مع شجاعة حضور مثل هذه،
the Peerzadas were able to conclude
استطاعت عائلة بيرزاده اختتام
their festival on schedule.
مهرجانهم في الوقت المحدد.
And then the next year,
في السنة التالية،
they lost all of their sponsors
خسروا كل مموليهم
due to the security risk.
بسبب خطورة الوضع الأمني.
So when I met them in 2010,
عندما قابلتهم سنة 2010،
they were in the middle of the first subsequent event
كانوا في منتصف الفعالية التالية
that they were able to have in the same venue,
والتي استطاعوا إقامتها في نفس المكان،
and this was the ninth youth performing arts festival
و كان ذلك تاسع مهرجان للفنون الاستعراضية للشباب
held in Lahore in a year when that city
يقام في لاهور في سنة كانت فيها المدينة
had already experienced 44 terror attacks.
قد تعرضت لـ 44 هجوم إرهابي.
This was a time when the Pakistani Taliban
كان ذلك في وقت بدأت فيه طالبان الباكستانية
had commenced their systematic targeting
استهدافاتها المنظمة
of girls' schools that would culminate
لمدارس الطالبات والتي بلغت ذروتها
in the attack on Malala Yousafzai.
بالهجوم على ملالا يوسف زاي.
What did the Peerzadas do in that environment?
ماذا فعلت عائلة بيرزاده في تلك البيئة؟
They staged girls' school theater.
أسسوا مسرحا مدرسيا للطالبات.
So I had the privilege of watching "Naang Wal,"
والتي كان لي شرف حضور" نانق ول "،
which was a musical in the Punjabi language,
مسرحية موسيقية باللغة البنجابية،
and the girls of Lahore Grammar School
أدت طالبات مدرسة قرامر في لاهور
played all the parts.
كل فصولها.
They sang and danced,
غنين و رقصن،
they played the mice and the water buffalo,
و أدين أدوار الفئران وفرس النهر،
and I held my breath, wondering,
حبست أنفاسي، وأنا تساءل
would we get to the end
إذا ما كنا سنرى نهاية
of this amazing show?
هذا العرض الرائع؟
And when we did, the whole audience
وعندما فعلنا، تنفس كل الحضور
collectively exhaled,
جميعاً الصعداء،
and a few people actually wept,
حتى أن البعض منهم بكى،
and then they filled the auditorium
بعدها ملؤوا القاعة
with the peaceful boom of their applause.
بقنبلة مسالمة من التصفيق.
And I remember thinking in that moment
وأتذكر تفكيري في تلك اللحظة
that the bombers made headlines here
أن المفجرين احتلوا صدارة العناوين
two years before
قبل سنتين هنا
but this night and these people
لكن مافعله هؤلاء الناس في هذه الليلة
are as important a story.
لا يقل أهمية عن ذلك .
Maria Bashir is the first and only
ماريا بشير هي االمرأة الأولى و الوحيدة
woman chief prosecutor in Afghanistan.
التي شغلت منصب مدعية عامة في أفغانستان.
She's been in the post since 2008
فُوّضت في 2008
and actually opened an office to investigate
وفتحت مكتباً للتحقيق
cases of violence against women,
في قضايا عنف ضد النساء،
which she says is the most important area
والتي تقول أنه المجال الأهم
in her mandate.
في تفويضها.
When I meet her in her office in Herat,
عندما قابلتها في مكتبها في هيرات،
she enters surrounded by
دخلت وهي محاطة
four large men with four huge guns.
بأربعة رجال عظام يحملون أربع أسلحة ضخمة.
In fact, she now has 23 bodyguards,
في الواقع،لديها الآن 23 حارسا شخصيا،
because she has weathered bomb attacks
لأنها تعرضت لهجوم تفجيري
that nearly killed her kids,
كاد أن يقتل أطفالها،
and it took the leg off of one of her guards.
ونجم عنه بتر ساق أحد حراسها.
Why does she continue?
لماذا تواصل عملها إذا؟
She says with a smile that that is the question
ردت بابتسامة وقالت أن هذا هو السؤال
that everyone asks—
الذي يطرحه الجميع--
as she puts it, "Why you risk not living?"
كما وصفته،" لماذا تخاطر بأن لا تحيا؟"
And it is simply that for her,
والأمر ببساطة هو كذلك بالنسبة لها،
a better future for all the Maria Bashirs to come
مستقبل أفضل لجميع "ماريا بشير" القادمات
is worth the risk,
يستحق هذه المخاطرة،
and she knows that if people like her
وهي تعرف أن الناس أمثالها
do not take the risk,
إن لم يخاطروا ،
there will be no better future.
فلن يكون هناك مستقبل أفضل.
Later on in our interview,
لاحقاً أثناء مقابلتنا،
Prosecutor Bashir tells me how worried she is
أخبرتني بشير المدعية العامة عن قلقها
about the possible outcome
بشأن النتيجة المحتملة
of government negotiations with the Taliban,
إذا قامت الحكومة بمفاوضات مع طالبان،
the people who have been trying to kill her.
المجموعة التي كانت تحاول قتلها.
"If we give them a place in the government,"
" لو أعطيناهم مكاناً في الحكومة،"
she asks, "Who will protect women's rights?"
تساءلت،" من سيحمي حقوق المرأة ؟ "
And she urges the international community
وحثت المجتمع العالمي
not to forget its promise about women
أن لا ينسى وعده بشأن المرأة
because now they want peace with Taliban.
لأنهم الآن يريدون السلام مع طالبان.
A few weeks after I leave Afghanistan,
بعد عدة أسابيع من مغادرتي أفغانستان،
I see a headline on the Internet.
رأيت عناوين على الانترنت.
An Afghan prosecutor has been assassinated.
أن مدعيا عاما أفغانيا تم قتله.
I google desperately,
فبحثت يائسة على غوغل،
and thankfully that day I find out
وحمداً لله توصلت في ذلك اليوم
that Maria was not the victim,
أن ماريا لم تكن هي الضحية،
though sadly, another Afghan prosecutor
لكن للأسف، مدع عام أفغاني آخر
was gunned down on his way to work.
تم قتله بالرصاص أثناء توجهه لمقر عمله .
And when I hear headlines like that now,
والآن عندما أسمع عناوين مثل تلك،
I think that as international troops
وأفكر في القوات الدولية
leave Afghanistan this year and beyond,
التي تغادر أفغانستان هذا العام والأعوام القادمة،
we must continue to care
أفكر أنه علينا أن نواصل اهتمامنا
about what happens to people there,
بما يحدث للناس هناك،
to all of the Maria Bashirs.
لكل من هم مثل ماريا بشير.
Sometimes I still hear her voice in my head
مازلت أسمع صوتها يتردد بداخلي أحياناً
saying, with no bravado whatsoever,
وهي تقول، بلا تبجح على الإطلاق،
"The situation of the women of Afghanistan
"وضع المرأة في افغانستان
will be better someday.
سيصبح أفضل يوماً ما.
We should prepare the ground for this,
يجب أن نقوم بتجهيز الأساس لذلك،
even if we are killed."
حتى لو قُتلنا."
There are no words adequate
ليست هناك كلمات مناسبة
to denounce the al Shabaab terrorists
لاستنكار ما فعلته مجموعة الشباب الإرهابية
who attacked the Westgate Mall in Nairobi
التي هاجمت مجمع"ويست جيت" التجاري في نيروبي
on the same day as a children's cooking competition
في نفس اليوم الذي كانت تقام فيه مسابقة طبخ للأطفال
in September of 2013.
في سبتمبر عام 2013.
They killed 67, including poets and pregnant women.
قتلوا 67 شخصاً،بمن فيهم شعراء ونساء حوامل.
Far away in the American Midwest,
في مكان بعيد في الوسط الغربي الأمريكي،
I had the good fortune of meeting Somali-Americans
كان لي شرف مقابلة صوماليين يحملون الجنسية الأمريكية
who were working to counter the efforts of al Shabaab
والذين يقومون بجهود مضادة لمجموعة الشباب
to recruit a small number of young people
في تجنيد عدد من صغار السن
from their city of Minneapolis
من مدينتهم مينيبوليس
to take part in atrocities like Westgate.
ليقوموا بأعمال وحشية مثل حادثة "ويست جيت".
Abdirizak Bihi's studious
ابن أخ عبدالرزاق بيهي كان طالباً مثابراً
17-year-old nephew Burhan Hassan
اسمه برهان حسن ذو 17 عاماً
was recruited here in 2008,
جُنّد هنا في 2008،
spirited to Somalia,
وخُطف إلى الصومال.
and then killed when he tried to come home.
وقُتل عندما حاول العودة إلى البلاد.
Since that time, Mr. Bihi,
منذ ذلك الوقت،والسيد بيهي،
who directs the no-budget Somali Education and Advocacy Center,
الذي يدير مركزاً تعليمياً ودعوياً بلا رأس مال في الصومال،
has been vocally denouncing the recruitment
يندد جهاراً بالتجنيد
and the failures of government
وبفشل الحكومة
and Somali-American institutions
والمراكز الصومالية الأمريكية
like the Abubakar As-Saddique Islamic Center
مثل مركز أبو بكر الصديق الإسلامي
where he believes his nephew was radicalized
والذي يعتقد أن ابن أخيه تطرّف هناك
during a youth program.
أثناء برنامج للفتيان.
But he doesn't just criticize the mosque.
لكنه لا ينتقد المسجد فحسب.
He also takes on the government
لكنه أيضاً يحمّل الحكومة
for its failure to do more
مسؤولية الفشل في بذل جهود أكبر
to prevent poverty in his community.
لمنع الفقر في مجتمعه.
Given his own lack of financial resources,
وبسبب افتقاره للمصادر المادية،
Mr. Bihi has had to be creative.
كان على السيد بيهي أن يكون مبدعاً.
To counter the efforts of al Shabaab
لمواجهة جهود مجموعة الشباب
to sway more disaffected youth,
في التأثير على الفتية الساخطين،
in the wake of the group's 2010 attack
ففي بداية هجومهم عام 2010
on World Cup viewers in Uganda,
على متابعي كأس العالم في أوغندا،
he organized a Ramadan basketball tournament
نظّم فعالية رمضانية لكرة السلة
in Minneapolis in response.
في مينيبوليس رداً على ذلك.
Scores of Somali-American kids came out
أتى العشرات من الصوماليين-الأمريكيين
to embrace sport
لممارسة الرياضة
despite the fatwa against it.
بالرغم من الفتوى بتحريمها.
They played basketball
لعبوا كرة السلة
as Burhan Hassan never would again.
والتي لن يلعبها برهان حسن أبداً.
For his efforts, Mr. Bihi has been ostracized
مقابل جهوده، نُبذ السيد بيهي
by the leadership of the Abubakar As-Saddique Islamic Center,
من طرف مدير مركز أبي بكر الصديق الإسلامي،
with which he used to have good relations.
والذي كانت تربطهما علاقة جيدة.
He told me, "One day we saw the imam on TV
أخبرني،" ذات يوم رأينا الإمام على التلفزيون
calling us infidels and saying,
يدعونا بالكفرة ويقول،
'These families are trying to destroy the mosque.'"
" تحاول هذه العائلات تدمير المسجد."
This is at complete odds
وهذا مخالف بالكامل
with how Abdirizak Bihi understands
لما يراه عبدالرزاق بيهي
what he is trying to do
و ما يحاول فعله
by exposing al Shabaab recruitment,
بفضح تجنيد مجموعة الشباب،
which is to save the religion I love
وهو حماية الدين الذي أحب
from a small number of extremists.
من عدد صغير من المتطرفين.
Now I want to tell one last story,
والآن أريد إخباركم بقصة أخيرة،
that of a 22-year-old law student in Algeria
عن طالبة قانون ذات 22 سنة في الجزائر
named Amel Zenoune-Zouani
تدعى أمل زينون زواني
who had the same dreams of a legal career
والتي كانت تحلم بمهنة قانونية
that I did back in the '90s.
مثل أحلامي تلك في التسعينات.
She refused to give up her studies,
رفضت التخلي عن دراستها،
despite the fact that the fundamentalists
بالرغم من أن الأصوليين الذين
battling the Algerian state back then
يصارعون الحكومة الجزائرية وقتها
threatened all who continued their education.
كانوا يهددون كل من يحاول أن يواصل تعليمه.
On January 26, 1997, Amel boarded the bus
في 26 يناير 1997،استقلت أمل الحافلة
in Algiers where she was studying
في الجزائر العاصمة حيث كانت تدرس
to go home and spend a Ramadan evening
عائدةً إلى البيت لتقضي ليلة رمضانية
with her family,
مع عائلتها،
and would never finish law school.
لكنها لم تعد بعدها أبداً لدراسة القانون.
When the bus reached the outskirts
عندما وصلت الحافلة إلى ضاحية
of her hometown, it was stopped
مدينتها، توقفت
at a checkpoint manned by men
عند نقطة تفتيش يرأسها رجال
from the Armed Islamic Group.
من المجموعة الإسلامية المسلحة.
Carrying her schoolbag,
أخذوا حقيبتها الدراسية،
Amel was taken off the bus
وأُجبرت على النزول من الحافلة
and killed in the street.
وقُتلت في الشارع.
The men who cut her throat
أخبر الرجال الذين قطعوا عنقها
then told everyone else,
الجميع بعد ذلك،
"If you go to university,
" إذا ذهبتم للجامعة،
the day will come when we will kill all of you
سيأتي اليوم الذي سنقتلكم فيه جميعا
just like this."
تماماً مثلها."
Amel died at exactly 5:17 p.m.,
قُتلت أمل على الساعة 5:17 مساءاً ،
which we know because when she fell in the street,
ونعرف ذلك لأنها عندما سقطت في الشارع،
her watch broke.
كُسرت ساعتها.
Her mother showed me the watch
أرتني والدتها الساعة
with the second hand still aimed
وعقرب الثواني مازال يشير
optimistically upward
بتفاؤل للأعلى
towards a 5:18 that would never come.
باتجاه 5:18 والتي لن تأتي أبداً.
Shortly before her death,
قبل مقتلها بقليل،
Amel had said to her mother of herself
قالت أمل لأمها عن نفسها
and her sisters,
وأخواتها،
"Nothing will happen to us, Inshallah, God willing,
" لن يحدث مكروه لنا،إن شاء الله،
you must know that we are dead for knowledge.
فيجب أن تعلمي أننا متنا من أجل العلم.
The loss of such a young woman is unfathomable,
فقدان شابة مثل هذه أمر يصعب فهمه،
and so as I did my research
وعندما قمت ببحثي
I found myself searching for Amel's hope again
وجدت نفسي أبحث عن أمل لأمل
I think I found it in two places.
وأعتقد أنني وجدته في مكانين.
The first is in the strength of her family
الأول هو في قوة تحمل عائلتها
and all the other families to continue telling their stories
والعائلات الآخرى في مواصلة رواية قصصهم
and to go on with their lives despite the terrorism.
واستمرار حياتهم بالرغم من وجود الإرهاب.
In fact, Amel's sister Lamia overcame her grief,
في الواقع ،تجاوزت لمياء أخت أمل مرحلة الحِداد
went to law school,
والتحقت بكلية القانون،
and practices as a lawyer in Algiers today,
وتعمل اليوم كمحامية في الجزائر العاصمة،
something which is only possible
وهو شيء لم يكن ممكناً
because the armed fundamentalists
لولم يُهْزَم المتطرفون المسلحون
were largely defeated in the country.
هزيمة نكراء في البلاد.
was everywhere that women and men
هو كل مكان تستمر فيه النساء والرجال
We must support all of those in honor of Amel
يجب أن ندعم كل هؤلاء تكريماً لأمل
who continue this human rights struggle today,
الذين يواصلون صراع حقوق الإنسان اليوم،
like the Network of Women Living Under Muslim Laws.
مثل شبكة "النساء الخاضعات للقوانين الاسلامية".
Cherifa Kheddar told me in Algiers,
شريفة خضّار في الجزائر،حين أخبرتني
it is not enough just to battle terrorism.
لا يكفي أن نقاوم الإرهاب فقط.
We must also challenge fundamentalism,
يجب أيضاً أن نتحدى الأصولية،
because fundamentalism is the ideology
لأن الأصولية هي الفكر
that makes the bed of this terrorism.
الذي يغذي هذا الإرهاب.
Why is it that people like her, like all of them
لِمَ لَمْ يكن من هم أمثالها، أمثالهم كلهم
are not more well known?
مشهورين؟
Why is it that everyone knows who Osama bin Laden was
لماذا يعرف الجميع من كان أسامة بن لادن
and so few know of all of those
بينما يعرف القليل عن هؤلاء
standing up to the bin Ladens in their own contexts.
الذين تصدوا لابن لادن بطريقتهم الخاصة.
We must change that, and so I ask you
يجب أن نغير ذلك، وأنا أطلب منكم
to please help share these stories
وأرجوكم أن تشاركوا هذه القصص
through your networks.
من خلال شبكاتكم.
Look again at Amel Zenoune's watch,
انظروا مرةً آخرى لساعة أمل زينون،
forever frozen,
الجامدة إلى الأبد،
and now please look at your own watch
والآن أنظروا من فضلكم إلى ساعتكم
and decide this is the moment that you commit
وقرروا من هذه اللحظة أنكم ستلتزمون
to supporting people like Amel.
بدعم الناس أمثال أمل.
We don't have the right to be silent about them
ليس لدينا الحق أن نبقى صامتين بشأنهم
because it is easier
لأنه من السهل فعل ذلك
or because Western policy is flawed as well,
أو لأن السياسة الغربية بها عيوب،
because 5:17 is still coming
بل لأن 5:17 مازالت قادمة
to too many Amel Zenounes
للكثير من أمثال أمل زينون
in places like northern Nigeria,
في مدن مثل شمال نيجيريا،
where jihadis still kill students.
حيث مازال الجهاديون يقتلون الطلاب .
The time to speak up in support of all of those
الوقت المناسب للحديث دعماً لكل هؤلاء
who peacefully challenge fundamentalism
الذين تحدّوا الأصولية والإرهاب بسلام
is now.
هو الآن.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.